Guide to the Women and Work Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Women and Work Collection
1978-1978
MS 1313
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.75
(9 boxes)
Typed transcripts (electrostatic copies) of interviews with women for the project: "The Twentieth Century Trade Union Woman: Vehicle for Social Change," conducted by the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (University of Michigan-Wayne State University) Program on Women and Work.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by last name of interviewee.
Scope and Contents
In 1978 the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (University of Michigan-Wayne State University) began issuing a series of transcripts of interviews conducted under the auspices of the Twentieth Century Trade Union Women Oral History Project. Some seventy-five women who had achieved positions of leadership in their unions or in the trade union movement were interviewed for the project. Transcripts of these interviews, published under the general title "The Twentieth Century Trade Union Woman: Vehicle for Social Change," make up this collection.
A few of the interviews were prepared in cooperation with other universities conducting similar projects, among them Pennsylvania State University, the Black Women Oral History Project of the Schlesinger Library at Radcliffe College, the Ohio Labor History Project, the Roosevelt University Oral History Project, the Southern Oral History Program, and the University of Iowa Oral History Project. Although a wide range of industries and their respective unions were surveyed, the unions most heavily represented are the Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union, the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, the Textile Workers Union, and the United Auto Workers.
The interviews, which are in the form of electrostatic copies, have been arranged alphabetically by the name of the woman interviewed; her affiliation, the name of the interviewer, and the date of the interview are indicated. An index to the interviews by union or political group is also included in this register. Four of the women interviewed - Marie Fese, Eula McGill, Julia Luna Mount, and Celia Pincus - have restricted their interviews, i.e., the transcripts may be read but permission to publish excerpts or quote from the text must be obtained from the interviewee.
INDEX OF UNIONS AND OTHER ORGANIZATIONS
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union - folder 29
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - folders 2, 10, 12, 26, 27, 36, 43, 45, 52, 54
American Federation of Labor - folder 44
American Federation of Labor - Congress of Industrial Organization - folder 32
American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees - folder 42
American Federation of Teachers - folder 15
American Labor Education Service - folder 17
Augusta Building Trades Council - folder 1
Brotherhood of Railway and Airline Clerks - folder 11
Communications Workers of America - folders 7, 55, 56
Domestic Workers of America - folder 41
Hotel and Restaurant Employees' and Bartenders' International Union - folder 48
Industrial Workers of the World - folder 5
International Brotherhood of Teamsters - folder 35
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union - folders 9, 13, 18, 19, 33, 46
International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union - folder 25
International Union of Electrical Workers - folder 3
International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America - See United Automobile Workers
National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees - folder 51
Office Employees' International Union - folder 21
Office Workers' Union - folder 53
Philadelphia Federation of Teachers - folder 39
Progressive Party - folder 49
Service Employees' International Union - folder 31
Textile Workers' Union of America - folders 34, 40, 47, 50
United Automobile Workers - folders 14, 16, 20, 37
United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing, and Allied Workers of America - folder 30
United Farm Workers - folder 8
United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers' International Union - folder 22
United Rubber Workers - folder 24
United Steelworkers of America - folder 38
Waitresses' Union - folder 6
Women's Trade Union League - folder 23
Women's Alliance to Gain Equality - folder 28
Young Women's Christian Association - folder 4
Working class -- Education; Labor unions -- United States -- African American membership; Labor unions -- United States; Women labor union members -- United States; Women -- Employment; United States -- Economic conditions; Labor movement -- Education; Labor -- Education; Barron, Sara, 1900-; Dubrow, Evelyn; Fredgant, Sara, 1900-; Peterson, Esther, 1906-1997; Robinson, Dollie Lowther; Wertheimer, Barbara M.; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; Textile Workers Union of America
- Inventory
  - Baker, Mary Blackwell - Augusta Building Trades Council - Interviewed by Constance Myers, 1977 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barron, Sara - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Barbara Wertheimer, 1976 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Callahan, Mary - International Union of Electrical Workers - Interviewed by Alice Hoffman and Karen Budd, 1976 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Christensen, Ethlyn - Young Women's Christian Association - Interviewed by Betsy Jameson, 1978 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cohen, Sophie - Industrial Workers of the World - Interviewed by Deborah Shaffer and Stewart Bird, 1977 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Compton, Beulah - Waitresses' Union - Interviewed by Elizabeth Case, 1977 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conroy, Catherine - Communications Workers of America - Interviewed by Elizabeth Balanoff, 1976 Aug/December (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - De La Cruz, Jessie - United Farm Workers - Interviewed by Anne Loftis, 1973 December 14 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dubrow, Evelyn - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union - Interviewed by Lydia Kleiner, 1976 August 21 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Elkuss, Mary Lawrence - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Gloria Gordon, 1976 October 21 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fese, Marie (1) - Brotherhood of Railway and Airline Clerks - Interviewed by Elizabeth Balanoff, 1978 June 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    General note
    (1) Permission required from interviewee for any quotes, citations, and/or utilization of material.
  - Fredgant, Sara - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Alice Hoffman and Karen Budd, 1976 June 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Graham, Charlotte - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union - Interviewed by Glenn Scott, 1978 August (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Haener, Dorothy - United Automobile Workers - Interviewed by Lyn Goldfarb, Lydia Kleiner, and Christine Miller, 1978 April 11 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Herstein, Lillian - American Federation of Teachers - Interviewed by Elizabeth Balanoff, 1970 October 26-1971 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Jeffrey, Mildred - United Automobile Workers - Interviewed by Ruth Meyerowitz, 1976 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jones, Brownie Lee - American Labor Education Service - Interviewed by Mary Frederickson, 1976 April 20 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Kemp, Maida Springer - International Ladies' Garment Workers - Union, Interviewed by Elizabeth Balanoff, 1977 January 4 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Kimmel, Elizabeth - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union - Interviewed by Glenn Scott, 1979 January 10 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Kraus, Dorothy and Henry - United Automobile Workers - Interviewed by Patricia Yeghissian, 1978 September 7 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Levitas, Mollie - Office Employees' International Union - Interviewed by Elizabeth Balanoff, 1970 Jul/December (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Lucia, Carmen - United Hatters, Cap and Millinary Workers International Union - Interviewed by Seth Widgerson and Bette Craig, 1976 July 26 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Luscomb, Florence - Women's Trade Union League - Interviewed by Brigid O'Farrell, 1976 July (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Lynch, Florence - United Rubber Workers - Interviewed by Debra Bernhardt, 1978 November 28 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - McElrath, Ah Quon - International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union - Interviewed by Marion Roffman, 1976 August 4 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - McGill, Eula (2) - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Jacquelyn Hall, 1976 February (Box 5, Folder 26)
    (2) Permission required from interviewee for any quotes, citations and/or utilization of material.
  - Maietta, Julia - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Alice Hoffman and Karen Budd, 1976 May 11 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Maupin, Joyce - Women's Alliance to Gain Equality (WAGE)- Interviewed by Patricia Yeghissian, 1978 July 16 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Merrill, Barbara - Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union - Interviewed by Elizabeth Balanoff, 1978 September 20 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Mount, Julia Luna (3) - United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing, and Allied Workers of America - Interviewed by Becca Wilson, 1978 October 5 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    (3) Permission required from interviewee for any quotes, citations and/or utilization of material.
  - Neal, Arline - Service Employees' International Union - Interviewed by Phyllis Boanes and Lyn Goldfarb, 1976 August 18 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Neal, Fannie Allen - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) Committee on Political Education - Interviewed by Marlene Hunt, 1977 May 27 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Newman, Pauline - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union - Interviewed by Barbara Wertheimer, 1976 November (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Nord, Elizabeth - Textile Workers' Union of America - Interviewed by Professor James Findlay, Gary Julik, Christina Simmons, and Judy Smith, 1975 November 12 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Palmquist, Rose Seiler - International Brotherhood of Teamsters - Interviewed by Mary Ellen Frank, 1977 June 1 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Peterson, Esther - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Martha Ross, 1977 August 13 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Peterson, Florence - United Automobile Workers - Interviewed by Ruth Meyerowitz, 1976 July 28 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Peurala, Alice - United Steelworkers of America - Interviewed by Elizabeth Balanoff, 1977 September 30 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Pincus, Celia (4) - Philadelphia Federation of Teachers - Interviewed by Alice Hoffman, 1976 April 27 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    (4) Permission required from interviewee for any quotes, citations and/or utilization of material.
  - Podojil, Antoinette - Textile Workers' Union of America - Interviewed by Lydia Kleiner, 1976 Jun/October (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Roberts, Geraldine - Domestic Workers of America - Interviewed by Donna Van Raaphorst, 1977 March 30-June 29 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Roberts, Lillian - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees - Interviewed by Susan Reverby, 1978 May 1 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Robinson, Dolly Lowther - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Bette Craig, 1976 July (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Scattergood, Margaret - American Federation of Labor - Interviewed by Alice Hoffman, 1976 December 3 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Schwenkmeyer, Frieda - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Bette Craig, 1976 August (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Segal, Bonnie Taylor - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union - Interviewed by Alice Hoffman, 1975 July 21; 1975 December 12 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Sullivan, Anna - Textile Workers' Union of America - Interviewed by Brigid O'Farrell, 1976 June 25 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Sweet, Gertrude - Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union - Interviewed by Shirley Tanzer, 1976 August 2 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Taylor, Pauline - Progressive Party - Interviewed by Deborah Bernhardt, 1978 August 17 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Thornburgh, Lucille - Textile Workers' Union of America - Interviewed by June Rostan, 1978 January 10 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Turner, Doris - National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees - Interviewed by Cindia Cameron, 1978 August 8 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Urdaneta, Regina - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Enid M. Valle, 1978 January 8 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Ward, Angela Gizzi - Office Workers Union - Interviewed by Sue Cobbie, 1977 January 26 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Wertheimer, Barbara Mayer - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Interviewed by Bette Craig, 1977 April-May (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Wiencek, Ruth - Communications Workers of America - Interviewed by Carol Bowie, 1976 June 2 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Wooding, Nelle - Communications Workers of America - Interviewed by John Schacht, 1970 March 24 (Box 9, Folder 56)